Finding Aid for Mullett Family Papers 1665-1924
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mullett Family papers 1665-1924, 1825-1924
Mullett family.
1 oversize folders
1 linear feet
Williamston, Ingham County, Michigan, family. Financial records, clippings, and correspondence relating to Mullett Farm and John Mullett, surveyor; extract, 1864, from Meridian Township Register Book; letterpress book, journal, and correspondence, 1852-1893, of John H. Forster, surveyor, agent for Pewabic Mining Company, Hancock, Mich., and later owner of Springbrook Farm, Ingham County, Michigan; diary, 1840-1841, of Catherine Hall; and map, 1859, of Mullett Farm; and photographs.
852069 Aa 2 Ac
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. John Husselman, Sr. (donor no. 4770 ) in 1969 and 1980 and from Mrs. Faith Mullett Ross (donor no. 5940 ) in 1978.
The collection is open for research.
The first member of the Mullett family to settle in Michigan was John Mullett who came to Detroit from Buffalo, New York in 1814. Here he achieved prominence as a surveyor, "helping to layout the city of Detroit and assisting in many of the government's original surveys of Michigan, Wisconsin, Illinois and Indiana." He also did much of the survey work for the plank road between Detroit and Grand Rapids. In 1849, he moved with his family to a farm near Williamston in Ingham County.
John Mullett and his wife had a large family, many of whom are represented in the Mullett family collection. There was Catherine Mullett, who later married B.F. Hall, an Aurora, Illinois banker. The son of B.F. and Catherine Hall was Robert Henry Hall (1837-1914), an 1860 graduate of West Point, who served as an infantry officer in f the Civil War, and then went on as an instructor at the U.S. Military Academy from 1871 to 1878. Hall continued on in the service to the rank of Brigadier General in the Regular Army by the time of his retirement in 1901. One of his last tours of duty was as general officer of volunteers in the Philippines during the Spanish American War.
Another child of John Mullett was Martha Mullett, who later married John Harris Forster. Forster was a mining engineer and agent for two different Upper Peninsula firms. He was responsible for building triangulation stations in the Upper Peninsula. Later he represented Sheldon and Columbian Copper in New York (1863, 1867-1869), Chicago (1867), and Salt Lake City (1869). He spent the last years of his life on a farm in Ingham County.
Other children of John Mullett included Charles F., Marshall C., Henry, and John Harvey Mullett, who, like his father, was a surveyor.
The Mullett family collection contains many useful descriptions of the state, and is a good source of information for some of the state's economic and topographic conditions during the 19th century. The papers, 1825-1936, are broken down into four series.
Subjects:
Aurora (Ill.); Copper mines and mining--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Farm life--Michigan--Ingham County.; Farmers--Michigan--Williamston.; Hancock (Mich.); Ingham County (Mich.); Meridian (Mich.); Michigan--Social life and customs--1831-1840.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1841-1850.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.; Mullett family.; Pewabic Mining Company.; Surveyors--Michigan.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.); Williamston (Mich.); Women--Illinois--Aurora.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Barbour Gymnasium (University of Michigan); Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Farms--Michigan--Williamston.; Fishing--Michigan.; Foch, Ferdinand, 1851-1929.; Harbors--Michigan--Petoskey--1891-1900.; Huron River (Oakland County-Monroe County, Mich.); Interiors.; Libraries--Michigan.; Mullett, John W., 1825-1902.; Nurses.; Petoskey (Mich.)--Harbors--1891-1900.; Picnics.; Railroad bridges.; St. Andrew's Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); University of Michigan. Library.; University of Michigan. School of Nursing. Class of 1912.; University of Michigan. University Hospital.; Williamston (Mich.)--Farms.; Williamston High School (Williamston, Mich.). Class of 1889.
Contributors:
Forster, John Harris, 1822-1894.; Hall, Catherine Mullett, b. 1817.; Mullett, John, 1786-1862.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- John Mullett (and John H. Mullett)
  The first series in the collection includes papers of John Mullett, 1825-1864, notably correspondence, surveyor's appointment materials, mortgages, deeds, and receipts. Some of these papers relate to the Mullett farm in Williamston. Because there was some confusion over what were the papers of John Mullett and what were the papers of his son John H. Mullett, it was decided to interfile the papers of father and son. Most of the series seems to be the papers of the son.
  - Correspondence 1825, 1827 (Box 1)
  - Surveyor appointments and related correspondence, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous surveys (Box 1)
  - Deeds 1847-1924 (Box 1)
  - Mortgages, etc. 1841-1900 (Box 1)
  - Notes, etc. 1839-1885 (Box 1)
  - Household bills and receipts 1836-1863 (Box 1)
  - Property tax bills and receipts
    - Ingham County 1838-1915 (Box 1)
    - Wayne County 1833-1853 (Box 1)
    - Cass, Jackson, Kent, Ottawa, Shiawassee Counties 1837-1859 (Box 1)
  - Road tax receipts 1825-1861 (Box 1)
  - School tax receipts 1838-1863 (Box 1)
  - List of names from register book for Meridian Township, Ingham County 1864, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea; include stock certificate, recipe, membership certificate, and Mullett genealogy70 (Box 1)
- John Harris and Martha Mullett Forster
  The second series, the John Harris and Martha Mullett Forster papers, 1840-1891, contain much family correspondence as well as some business correspondence, deeds and essays. Included within this series is a letterpress book written by Harris while an agent for the Pewabic Mining Company, 1860-1862. Considerable correspondence between Forster and his wife is to be found, as the former wrote regularly while working in the Upper Peninsula and on business trips.
  - Correspondence, business
    - 1852-1885 (Box 1)
    - 1889-1893 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, family (Box 1)
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - Tattered and incomplete letters
    - 1845-1847 (Box 1)
    - 1851-1853 (Box 1)
    - 1854-1856 (Box 1)
    - 1857-1859 (Box 1)
    - 1860-1862 (Box 1)
    - 1863-1864 (Box 1)
    - 1867-1869 (Box 1)
  - Deeds 1859-1887 (Box 1)
  - Documents, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Letterpress book written as an agent for Pewabic Mining Company, Hancock, Mich. 1860-1862 (Box 1)
  - Farm Journal written at Springbrook Farm, Ingham County 1877-1881 (Box 1)
  - Essays "Our Michigan" and "Narrow Gauge VB. Broad Gauge" 1891 (Box 1)
- Hall Family
  The Hall family papers, 1840-1938, contain correspondence and other materials of Catherine "Kate" Mullett (Mrs. Benjamin F.) Hall, her son, General Robert Henry Hall, while serving in Arizona and Texas, and two of his three sons, Robert F. and Harris Hall, while they were at military prep school from 1886 to 1889. This series also includes some military records relating to Robert H. Hall's career, and a diary written by Catherine from 1840 to 1841.
  - Catherine "Kate" Mullett Hall
    - Correspondence 1869-1888 (Box 1)
    - Diary 1840-1841 (Box 1)
  - Robert F. Hall, letter to his cousin, Charles Mullett November 3, 1938 (Box 1)
  - Robert F. and Harris Hall, correspondence to parents while at Tivoli-on-the-Hudson, military prep school 1886-1889 (Box 1)
  - Robert Henry Hall, military records and personal correspondence 1855-1890 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous family materials
  The last series includes miscellaneous materials, 1832-1924, of family-related individuals, including deeds, journals, poems, and historical sketches. In this group is a letter, dated 1665, committing Thomas Ellwood and other Quakers to jail at Wicomb (Wycombe), Buckinghamshire, copied by Ellwood from an original signed by Ambrose Benet, and a fragment of a document in the handwriting of Quaker leader George Fox.
  - Sarah Bonine, journal and poems (Box 1)
  - Bonine family
    - Newspaper clippings and articles (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, poetry, and family reunion lists (Box 1)
  - Clay E. Call family, deeds, etc. 1911-1924 (Box 1)
  - East family, historical sketch 1908 (Box 1)
  - Thomas Ellwood letter 1665, committing Thomas Ellwood and other Quakers to jail at Wicomb (Wycombe), Buckinghamshire (Box 1)
    (copied by Ellwood from an original signed by Ambrose Benet, and a fragment of a document in the handwriting of Quaker leader George Fox)
  - George Fox, letter purportedly written for Ambrok Benet 1665 (Box 1)
    (addressed to the House of Corrections in Wicomb)
  - Osborn family
    - Charles, passport 1832 (Folder 1)
    - Narcissa, memorial 1836 (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (includes genealogy materials and unidentified 1871 letter)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Map of Mullett Farm, Ingham County 1859 (Folder 1)
  - Marriage certificate of James Bonine and Hannah East October 21, 1824 (Folder 1)